

#### DATA ENGINEER · PH.D. CANDIDATI

Lebanon, Baabda, Al Hadat

■ hadi.fadlullah@gmail.com | Ahttps://hadifadl.github.io | □ HadiFadl | 当 Hadi | □ hadi-fadlallah | ● @hadifadl2 | Madi-fadlullah | ● Hadi | Hadi |

### **Summary** \_

Ph.D. Candidate, Data Engineer, and Business Intelligence Developer. I have been working with SQL Server (and related technologies) for more than 10 years. I am one of the top ETL and SQL Server Integration Services contributors at Stackoverflow.com. Besides, I am a Technical Author at SQLShack.com.

### **Education**

### Lebanese University & Saint-Joseph University of Beirut

Beirut, Lebanon

Ph.D. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE / DATA SCIENCE

Oct. 2019 - present

 A Cooperative Ph.D. between the Doctoral School of Science and Technology at the Lebanese University, and the Faculty of Sciences at the Saint-Joseph University of Beirut

### **Lebanese University, Faculty of Sciences**

Beirut, Lebanon

M.S. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND RISK MANAGEMENT

Sep. 2017 - Sep. 2018

• Research Master's degree

• Rank: 1/17

#### Lebanese University, Faculty of Economics and Business Administration

Beirut, Lebanon

M.S. IN BUSINESS COMPUTING

Sep. 2012 - Sep. 2013

Professional Master's degree

Rank: 4/17

#### Lebanese University, Faculty of Economics and Business Administration

Beirut, Lebanon

MASTERY (MAÎTRISE) IN BUSINESS COMPUTING

Sep. 2010 - Sep. 2011

#### Lebanese University, Faculty of Economics and Business Administration

Beirut, Lebanon

B.S. IN BUSINESS COMPUTING

Sep. 2007 - Sep. 2010

# **Work Experience**

### **Munchy Bytes software solutions**

Beirut, Lebanon Oct. 2014 - present

Data Engineer & BI Developer

- · Design and Development of ETL/ELT solutions.
- · Implementing Data Quality solutions.
- Databases and Data warehouses development.
- · Designing reports and Analytics.
- · Database administration.
- Implementing Big data technologies.

Self-Employed Beirut, Lebanon

DEVELOPER Jan. 2010 - Dec. 2019

- My latest projects was developing an eco-system called ORADIEX for radiation data engineering at the Lebanese Atomic Energy Commission (LAEC-CNRS) and data reporting services for the Lebanese University.
- Contributing to open-source projects (SchemaMapper, EzApi)
- Developed several applications using Microsoft technologies
- Developing Business intelligence projects using SQL Server BI Tools
- Querying and administering databases using Oracle 11g, SQL server 2005 ... 2016
- Computer science private teacher (Databases, ETL, VB.Net, SQL)

#### **Lebanese Atomic Energy Commission (LAEC-CNRS)**

Beirut, Lebanon

RESEARCH INTERN

REPORT DEVELOPER

Apr. 2018 - Sep. 2018

- The objective of this internship is to develop a scalable solution called RaDEn for engineering radiation data.
- Used Technologies: Hadoop, Spark, Kafka, Flume, InfluxDb, Grafana, Hive.

### **Diab Accounting and Auditing Agency**

Beirut, Lebanon Feb. 2016 - Oct. 2016

• Building reports using SQL Server Reporting Services.

DECEMBER 4, 2020 HADI FADLALLAH - CURRICULUM VITAE

**World Compu** Beirut, Lebanon

COMPUTER TECHNICIAN

• Diagnosis of desktop, application, networking and infrastructures issues.

· Computer maintenance.

Self-Employed Beirut, Lebanon

PRIVATE TEACHER

· Private Math and Physics teacher.

**Magic Photo** Beirut, Lebanon

DATA ENTRY

· Data Entry at the merchandise warehouse.

Oct. 2007 - Sep. 2009

Aug. 2009 - Jul. 2012

Sep. 2007 - Nov. 2007

## **Writing**

**SQL Shack** California, USA

TECHNICAL AUTHOR

Aug. 2019 - present

- Writing articles about SQL Server and related technologies.
- https://www.sqlshack.com/author/hadi

**Towards Data Science** Ontario, Canada

- May. 2018 present • Writing articles about Information Technology and Big Data.
- https://towardsdatascience.com/@hadi-fadlullah

**Data Developers** Beirut, Lebanon

PERSONAL BLOG

Mar. 2018 - present

- A blog with periodic posts about Programming and Business Intelligence.
- https://data-dev.blogspot.com/

# Extracurricular Activity \_\_\_\_

**Nooreed Connect** Beirut, Lebanon

ONLINE INSTRUCTOR

Jun. 2020 - present

- · On-demand private online tutoring
- · Providing on-demand career information private sessions

#### Stack overflow community

CONTRIBUTOR Oct. 2016 - present

- Provided more than 1400 posts (SQL, SQL Server, SSIS, ETL, VB.NET, C-Sharp, Excel, SQL Server data tools ...)
- One of the top answerers in SQL Server Integration Services (SSIS) and ETL.
- · Received the SQL Server, SSIS, and ETL gold badges.
- https://stackoverflow.com/users/7031230/hadi

### **Publications**

### ORADIEX: A Big Data-driven smart framework for real-time surveillance and analysis of individual exposure to radioactive pollution

Versailles, France

2ND INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON BIG DATA AND CYBER-SECURITY INTELLIGENCE, BDCSINTELL 2019

Dec 2019

RaDEn: A Scalable and Efficient Radiation Data Engineering

Beirut, Lebanon

1ST INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON BIG DATA AND CYBER-SECURITY INTELLIGENCE, BDCSINTELL 2018

Dec. 2018

# Conferences & Seminars

### BDCSIntell'2019 by Intelligencia R & D

Versailles, France

PRESENTER FOR <A BIG DATA DRIVEN SMART FRAMEWORK FOR REAL-TIME SURVEILLANCE AND ANALYSIS OF INDIVIDUAL EXPOSURE TO RADIOACTIVE POLLUTION>

Dec 2019

**Data Engineering Seminar by USAL university** 

Beirut, Lebanon

PRESENTER FOR < BUILDING A DATA ENGINEERING FRAMEWORK FOR REAL-TIME RADIATION DATA>

Nov. 2019

### Skills & Interests

- My primary expertise is in Business Intelligence using Microsoft BI Suite, especially in Integration Services.
- · I spend my spare time on answering questions and solving programming problems on "Stackoverflow.com" Q&A website, and I am one of the two top answerers in ETL and SSIS.
- I have many contributions to open source projects.
- In 09-2019, I was nominated for the Microsoft MVP Award due to my contributions to the community.
- · I am familiar with different programming languages such as C-Sharp, VB.NET, VBA, SQL, T-SQL, PL-SQL, and Python.
- I worked with different database management systems such as SQL Server, Oracle, MySQL, SQLite, Microsoft Access, InfluxDB, Cassandra. In addition to some Big Data technologies such as Hadoop, Kafka, Spark, Flume, Sqoop, Zookeeper.
- I have enrolled in many computer sciences online courses on IBM Cognitive Class, Datacamp, Udacity, Pluralsight, and Udemy.
- · Arabic is my mother tongue, and I am right in French and English; written and oral.

### **Certifications**

#### **Machine Learning**

STANFORD ONLINE 4 Dec 2020

· Statement of accomplishment

#### **Data Analyst with Python**

DATACAMP 26 Jun 2019

· Statement of accomplishment

### **Python Programmer**

DATACAMP 15 Mar 2018

Statement of accomplishment

### **Projects**

### Building an on-premise Big Data cluster under Windows operating system

Beirut, Lebanon

MUNCHY BYTES

Apr. 2019 - May. 2020

• The project goal is to build a Big Data cluster (Hadoop, Hive, Pig) on Windows 10 operating system.

### **Lebanese University Presidency Reporting Services**

Beirut, Lebanon

SELF-EMPLOYED

Feb. 2018 - May. 2019

- Designing and building reports for the Lebanese University Presidence.
- The main technologies used are Microsoft SQL Server, Microsoft Access, and Power BI.

#### MetaCube: SQL Server Analysis Services multidimensional databases metadata reader

Beirut, Lebanon

MUNCHY BYTES

Apr. 2018

 MetaCube is a tool that can be used to read the SQL Server Analysis Server Objects using AMO assemblies and map each object to the related directory and configuration files located in the server data directory (DataDir property).

### ORADIEX: A Big Data driven smart framework for real-time surveillance and analysis of individual exposure to radioactive pollution

Beirut, Lebanon

LEBANESE ACTOMIC ENERGY COMISSION (LAEC-CNRS)

Apr. 2018

- · This project is considered as the second phase of RadEn project to improve visualization layer and data retrieval operations and to store the processed data in a NOSQL database.
- · We used Big Data technologies such as Hadoop, Kafka, Flume, Sqoop, Hive and Spark, InfluxDB (NoSQL), Grafana.

### SchemaMapper: C-Sharp Schema mapping class library

Beirut, Lebanon

MUNCHY BYTES

Feb. 2019 - Apr. 2019

• SchemaMapper is a data integration class library that facilitates data import process from external sources having different schema definitions. It replaces creating many integration services packages by writing few lines of codes.

### EzAPI2016: SSIS package generator

Beirut, Lebanon

SELF-EMPLOYED

Feb. 2019 - Mar. 2019

· Contributing in EzApi which is an SQL Server Integration Services automation library written in C-Sharp created by Microsoft in order to facilitate this process instead of using SQL Server Client SDK assemblies which are harder to understand. My contribution was to add some functionalities related to Flat files manipulation.

# RaDEn: A Scalable and Efficient Platform for Radiation Data Engineering in Real-time to Forecast Events

Beirut, Lebanon

Apr. 2018 - Sep. 2018

LEBANESE ATOMIC ENERGY COMISSION (LAEC-CNRS)

• RaDEn is a scalable solution for engineering radiation data. RaDEn consists of data lake underlying techniques that enables to process and store massive scale unstructured data that moves with high-speed from sensors to data lake. The data lake will be developed with the capability of staging data at different processing level and enable the analysts to perform various analysis such as predicting radiation level.

• We used Big Data technologies such as Hadoop, Kafka, Flume, Sqoop, Hive and Spark.

Pearls Dental Software Beirut, Lebanon

Munchy Bytes

Pearls Dental Software is a flexible and user friendly solution for dental clinics.
Developed using VB.NET, SQL Server, Winforms, Entity Framework, LINQ.

Microsoft Access databases metadata reader

Beirut, Lebanon

SELF-EMPLOYED

Jun. 2017 - Jul. 2017

Jan. 2017 - Jan. 2018

• A small open-source application used to read Microsoft Access databases metadata.

#### Integration Services packages (.dtsx) metadata reader

Beirut, Lebanon

SELF-EMPLOYED

Mar. 2017 - Jun. 2017

• An application used to read .dtsx files metadata without installing SQL Server Integration Services.

Post Office application Beirut, Lebanon

**Munchy Bytes**Mar. 2016 - Aug. 2016

The goal was to build a application that handles all transfer operations done in post offices and to manage all customers and suppliers information.

• Developed using VB.NET, SQL Server, Winforms, Entity Framework, LINQ.

### **Enhancing the performance of K-Means algorithm**

Beirut, Lebanon Apr. 2013 - Sep. 2013

LEBANESE UNIVERSITY

• Project made in fulfillment of the requirements for a Master professional degree in Business Computing. It's goal is to improve an existing

K-Means algorithm written in C-Sharp using multi-threading technology in order to provide a high-performance solution with acceptable cost.

• Developed using C-Sharp, WPF.

• Developed using C-Sharp, WFT.

#### Freecom.lb Inventory Management System

Beirut, Lebanon

SELF-EMPLOYED

Sep. 2011 - Apr. 2012

• The goal was to build a system for tracking inventory levels, orders, sales and deliveries. It can also be used in the manufacturing industry to create a work order, bill of materials and other production-related documents.

• Developed using VB.NET, SQL Server, and Winforms

### **Boutique: Management System of a Trading Establishment**

Beirut, Lebanon

LEBANESE UNIVERSITY

Apr. 2010 - Sep. 2010

- · Project made in fulfillment of the requirements for a Bachelor degree in Business Computing,
- Developed using VB.NET, SQL Server, and Winforms